Jerome Chodorov Papers
Jerome Chodorov Papers
1941-1967
Chodorov, Jerome.
9 linear ft.
American playwright, director, short story author and librettist. Collection contains manuscripts of plays, screenplays, teleplays, and a few short stories; also a small amount of biographical material, correspondence and ephemera.
2750912
Biographical History
Jerome Chodorov (1911-2004) was an American playwright, librettist and director.
Born in New York City to Harry and Lena (Simmons) Chodorov, Jerome attended George Washington High School and then began his writing career as a journalist in the 1930s. By 1942 he had written at least seven plays or screenplays. Following a three-year hiatus from 1942 to 1945, during which time he served as a captain in the United States Air Force, he returned to writing, producing plays, screenplays, teleplays and short stories. His Wonderful Town won the 1953 New York Drama Critics Circle Award and the Outer Circle Award. Chodorov also collaborated on several productions with Joseph Fields, as well as one with novelist and playwright Joseph Heller ( Spy Story) and another with cartoonist Mell Lazarus ( The Boss Is Crazy Too).
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Jerome Chodorov Papers consists primarily of manuscripts of plays, screenplays, teleplays, and a few short stories, many with extensive revisions. The collection also contains a small amount of biographical material, correspondence and ephemera.
In many cases the title of a play changed in the course of writing and revising. Where it was possible to determine dates, the latest title was chosen under which to group the manuscripts of a single play. Earlier titles are given in the inventory below, with a cross-reference to the final title chosen for grouping.
Personal correspondence related to a particular play is filed with the manuscripts for that play. Items of interest include correspondence between Chodorov and Pearl S. Buck (Box 2, Christine), between Chodorov and Joshua Logan (Box 1, Blood, Sweat and Stanley Poole; Box 18, personal correspondence, 1961), and a letter from Chodorov to Otto Preminger (Box 18, personal correspondence, 1962).
Arrangement of the Collection
Manuscripts are in alphabetical order by title and within that chronologically by date of creation, where possible to determine (e.g., outline followed by drafts followed by final versions). Correspondence and notes relating to a particular play are filed with the manuscripts.
Subject and Genre Headings
Dance and theatre; Chodorov, Jerome.; Dramatists, American -- 20th century.; Librettists -- United States.; Correspondence.; Manuscripts (document genre); Scripts (documents); Dramatists.; Librettists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Unspecified, 1967.
Inventory
- Biographical information
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Manuscripts
  - An Amazing Event, See Three Bags Full
  - An Astounding Event, See Three Bags Full
  - Barnaby and Mr. O'Malley, 1962; typescript, correspondence (Box 1)
  - Barnum, May 1963; typescript and handwritten early and final drafts, outlines, many with revisions; 6 folders (Box 1)
  - Bascom Barlow, See Three Bags Full
  - The Big Ditch, 1954; outline typescript; Act I typescript with revisions; notes; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Blood, Sweat and Stanley Poole, 1961; 1963; carbon copy; correspondence (Box 1)
  - The Blue Coast, See Chez Francois
  - The Boss is Crazy Too, undated; carbon copy of first draft with revisions (Box 2)
  - Chez Francois, 1960; mimeo; carbon copy; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Christine, 1959-1960; fragments; carbon copies with revisions; correspondence (Box 2)
  - Cote d'Azur, See Chez Francois
  - Duchess and the Smugs, See Chez Francois
  - Dumas and Son
    - Outlines, notes and correspondence, 1964 (Box 2)
    - Outlines, drafts, notes and correspondence, 1964-1966; typescript, carbon and manuscript drafts both complete and of individual acts and scenes, many with revisions; 12 folders (Box 3)
    - Drafts and fragments, 1966; typescript, carbon and manuscript drafts, many with revisions; 10 folders (Box 4)
    - Fragments, 1967; undated; typescript, many with revisions; 6 folders (Box 5)
  - The French Touch, circa 1946; bound volume (Box 6)
  - Fun and Games, See Three Bags Full
  - A Funny Game, See Three Bags Full
  - The Girl in Pink Tights, 1953; mimeograph copy (Box 6)
  - The Great Waltz, 1965; undated; typescripts and xerox and mimeograph copies, many with revisions; Wright and Forrest rehearsal script, with annotations; notes and correspondence; 7 folders (Box 6)
  - A Hero's Life
    - Revisions and rewrites, notes, 1960; 1962,; undated; carbon, xerox and thermofax copies (Box 6)
    - Early versions, fragments, undated; typescripts and carbon copies, many with revisions; 3 folders (Box 7)
  - How Like a God, See Olympus 7-0000
  - I Had a Ball, 1964; mimeo of 2d draft; fragments; 2 carbon copies with revisions; carbon copy of album narration; 3 folders (Box 7)
  - Idiot's Delight, undated; notes (Box 7)
  - Impasse de la fidelite, 1961; rough copy; carbon copy; typescript; 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Junior Miss
    - Manuscript, 1941; carbon copy (Box 7)
    - Bound volume, 1944 (Box 8)
  - Junior Miss Goes to War, undated; carbon copy (Box 8)
  - Kitty, 1963-1964; undated; Act III with revisions; carbon copy of Act III; fragments; correspondence; notes; 3 folders (Box 8)
  - The Major and the Private, 1964; undated; drafts; fragments; many with revisions; 6 folders (Box 8)
  - A Mother's Kisses
    - Drafts, fragments, 1965-1966; carbon copies, typescripts, many with revisions; 9 folders (Box 9)
    - Drafts, fragments, 1966; typescripts, handwritten and mimeo copies, many with revisions; 9 folders (Box 10)
    - Drafts, fragments, 1966-1967; typescripts, mimeo and carbon copies, many with revisions; 3 folders (Box 11)
  - My Indian Family, See Christine
  - My Sister Eileen, circa 1946; bound volume (Box 11)
  - An Officer and a Gentleman, See The Major and the Private
  - Oh Men! Oh Women!, 1966; drafts of pilot script; typescripts, handwritten, carbon copies; 5 folders (Box 11)
  - Olympus 7-0000, 1966; 2nd and final drafts, fragments; typescripts and carbon and mimeo copies, many with revisions (Box 11)
  - Panama Sweepstakes, See The Big Ditch
  - The Ponder Heart, 1956; 1962,; 1966; drafts of teleplay, many with revisions; published material, clippings; bound volume; 4 folders (Box 12)
  - Profile, undated; outline for story; typescript, handwritten (Box 12)
  - Ride the Wind, undated; story; carbon copy (Box 12)
  - Ring Lardner, undated; typescript (Box 12)
  - Sailor Beware, See The Big Ditch
  - Spy Story, 1963; undated; outlines, drafts, treatments; 6 folders (Box 12)
  - The Student Prince
    - Drafts, fragments, correspondence, notes, sketches, 1966; handwritten, typescript, and carbon copies, many with revisions (Box 13)
    - Drafts, fragments, correspondence, 1966; typescripts, also xerox, mimeo and carbon copies, many with revisions (Box 14)
  - That Prince Wales, See Spy Story
  - That Side of Him, undated; story; handwritten and typescript, manuscripts with revisions (Box 14)
  - Three Bags Full
    - Drafts, 1965; includes alternate titles An Astounding Event, An Amazing Event; handwritten and typescript manuscripts and carbon copies, many with revisions; 6 folders (Box 14)
    - Drafts, 1965; includes alternate titles An Astounding Event, An Amazing Event, Bascom Barlow; typescripts and mimeo and carbon copies, many with revisions; 7 folders (Box 15)
    - Drafts, 1966; includes alternate titles A Funny Game, Fun and Games, and Oscar; typescripts and mimeo and carbon copies, many with revisions; 5 folders (Box 16)
  - Three Little Girls at School, 1941; carbon copy (Box 16)
  - Weismann on Weizmann, 1962-1963; mimeo copy with revisions; fragments; notes; correspondence (Box 16)
  - Wonder Wheel, undated; mimeo copy (Box 16)
    See also I Had a Ball
  - Wonderful Town, 1962-1963; mimeo copy; correspondence (Box 16)
  - The World's Biggest Caper (and How It Grew), 1966; story; typescript with revisions, also xerox copy; correspondence (Box 17)
  - The World is Mine, See Dumas and Son
  - Zero Hour — One Half, 1963; typescripts as well as carbon, xerox and mimeo copies of outline and numerous drafts, many with revisions; notes; correspondence; 10 folders (Box 17)
- Correspondence
  - Personal, 1959-1962 (Box 17)
  - Personal, 1963-1964; 1966 (Box 18)
  - Of others, 8 Jan 1944 (Box 18)
- Ephemera
  - Clippings, Aug 1962; Aug 1963 (Box 18)
- Duplicates
  - Miscellaneous duplicate material, 4 folders (Box 18)